<?xml-stylesheet href="Balisage-1-3-xsl/balisage-proceedings-html.xsl" type="text/xsl" ?>
<!--* I've got the Balisage-1-3-xsl directory symlinked. *-->
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.2">
<title>Interactivity Three Ways</title>
<info>
  <abstract>
    <para>This paper describes three different technologies that can
    be used to add interactivity to a document presented on the web:
    “plain old JavaScript”, Saxon-JS, and XForms. A specific feature
    is implemented in each system so that the differences between
    similar implementations across these three platforms can be observed.</para>
  </abstract>
  <author>
    <personname>
      <firstname>Norman</firstname>
      <surname>Walsh</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
      <orgname>Saxonica</orgname>
    </affiliation>
  </author>
  <author>
    <personname>
      <firstname>C. M.</firstname>
      <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
    </personname>
    <affiliation>
      <orgname>Black Mesa Technologies</orgname>
    </affiliation>
  </author>
  <keywordset role="author">
    <keyword>XForms</keyword>
    <keyword>JavaScript</keyword>
    <keyword>Saxon-JS</keyword>
  </keywordset>
  <pubdate>2021-07-16</pubdate>
</info>

<section xml:id="introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>One of the most obvious differences between documents physically
printed on pages of paper and documents displayed on electronic
devices is that the latter can be interactive in ways that the former
cannot.
More than 50 years ago, this is what convinced Ted Nelson and
others that when used well computers would dramatically change
our relation with text.
What kinds of interactivity are possible, and to what extent
interactivity adds value to a document, are challenging questions that
require careful analysis.</para>

<para>Deciding that some specific interactive feature would add value
immediately raises a new challenge: how is that feature going to be realized?
</para>

<para>In this paper, we look at three different technologies that can
be used to add interactivity to a document presented on the web:
“plain old JavaScript”, Saxon-JS, and XForms. We examine a specific
feature and compare the differences between similar implementations across
these three platforms.</para>

<section xml:id="background">
<title>Background</title>

<para>When a conference is an in-person event at a particular location,
there’s relatively little ambiguity in the schedule. If the clock on
the wall at breakfast reads 9:45am and the first talk is scheduled for
10:00am, you have fifteen minutes.</para>

<para>The schedule for a virtual conference with attendees in many
different time zones is another matter. In principle, you can publish
the schedule in a single time zone and everyone can add or subtract
the necessary offset to get “local time”. If the first talk is
scheduled for 10:00am, in Rockville, and the clock on the wall at
breakfast reads 9:45am, you have fifteen minutes &#x2014; if you are
in Rockville, or anywhere else on Eastern Daylight Time. If the clock
is on Mountain Time because it and you are located in Denver, you’ve
missed that talk!</para>

<para>Ask anyone who has participated regularly in activities
organized simultaneously across several time zones and they will tell
you stories about when they got it wrong or their colleagues
did.</para>

<para>It’s just easier if you can see the times in your time
zone.</para>

<para>For Balisage 2020, Norm attempted to make the Balisage schedule
interactive such that a user could pick a timezone and the “schedule
at a glance” table would be updated so that it displayed the times of
the talks translated into that timezone.</para>

<para>The challenge at that time was to see if this could be done
using entirely native JavaScript APIs (no third party libraries
allowed), in a relatively straightforward way, that would work on many
modern browsers.</para>

<para>It turned out that a couple of decades into the twenty-first
century, this was a quite practical task. The complete solution was
achieved in just under 200 lines of code. (Lines of code is arguably a
poor metric generally, but this gives a sense of the magnitude. You
could just about squeeze the whole thing onto the front and back of a
single sheet of paper and it would still be legible.)
</para>

<para>This year, the challenge is to achieve the same results using
Saxon-JS and XForms. Then we’ll examine how those solutions compare.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="constraints">
<title>Constraints</title>

<para>The first and most significant constraint is that adding the
interactive schedule must not change the editorial process for
producing the schedule page in any <emphasis>significant</emphasis>
way. This is a perfectly fair and reasonable constraint. There is an
existing process and retraining everyone who updates that page is
beyond the scope of this project.</para>

<para>Luckily, as we’ll see in the next section, the Balisage
organizers understand the value of markup and the page is already
structured for reuse. And we aren’t forbidden from making any
changes to the markup on the page, only those that would significantly interfere
with the editorial process.</para>

<para>There are two additional constraints that stem from our requirement
not to change the editorial process:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The rendering has to be done in the browser. The data source is
markup in an otherwise static HTML page. Storing the schedule in a
database and rendering it from a server would open up new and
different avenues of approach, but we aren’t considering those here.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The table itself is authored by hand. The talks have semantic
markup that we can use, but there are other things in the schedule
with no corresponding description: the markup of the “Description”
column, the schedule entry for Balisage Bard, closing comments, etc.</para>
<para>If we were starting from scratch, it might be practical to define
declarative markup for the whole schedule and generate the table directly
from that markup, but <!-- that approach is not open to us. --> we are
not starting from scratch.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>The freedom we’ve given ourselves to make “insignificant”
changes to the page allows us to configure the schedule-at-a-glance
table so that it will be easier to process. These changes only have to
be done once and have no impact on the other editorial changes to the
table.</para>

<para>First, we can add some markup to each cell in the “time” column
to identify the time of the talk in a machine-readable way:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<time datetime="2020-07-27T14:00:00-04:00">14:00</time>]]></programlisting>

<para>The <code>datetime</code> attribute contains an ISO 8601 value for
time. This value includes a timezone and represents the moment to display, but we
can assume they’ll all be in the timezone of Rockville, MD.
(The content of the <code>time</code> element is the displayed value, which will
change as a function of the selected local timezone.)</para>

<para>Additionally, we can add a <code>data-slot</code> attribute to
each table cell where a talk occurs. The presence of that attribute
identifies that a talk should be injected into this cell and the value
of the attribute identifies the talk.</para>

<para>Markup for the table cell for the talk on Monday at 10:00am is
</para>
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<td row-span="2" data-slot="Monday/10:00"></td>]]></programlisting>
<para>
The <code>data-slot</code> attribute identifies the talk by day and
time, not by its XML identifier, to protect the schedule-at-a-glance
against errors if the schedule changes at the last minute.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="requirements">
<title>Requirements</title>

<para>For the purposes of this paper, the requirements below have
been identified.</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Each talk is to be summarized with its title and author (including a link to
their bio, if it’s available). The abstract should appear as a popup or “tool tip”.
The title and author are separated by an em-dash (—). If multiple authors are
present, they are separated by commas.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the talk identified by the <code>data-slot</code> attribute has no authors,
the class “<code>lb</code>” must be added to the class attribute for its cell.
(This identifies “late breaking” slots which are colored differently by the CSS.)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If there is no talk corresponding to the <code>data-slot</code> value,
the class “<code>none</code>” must be added to the class attribute for its cell.
Additionally, the contents of the cell must be “No talk scheduled.”
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>The table has two controls, a <code>select</code> with options for the
timezone and a checkbox for selecting am/pm or 24 hour time display.
The times in the first column of the table must be adjusted according to these
values. The <code>value</code> of each select <code>option</code> is the
timezone offset expressed as +/-HH:MM.
</para>
<para>The select has the id “<code>tz</code>”, the checkbox has the id
“<code>clock24</code>”.<!--* clok24 or clock24? *--></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>When the timezone is changed, all of the times must be adjusted for the
newly selected timezone. If the checkbox is changed, all of the times must be
adjusted for the corresponding am/pm or 24 hour time display.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>When the timezone is changed, the value of the “clock24” updates
automatically. It is unselected for timezones that have a negative
offset and selected for all others. This corresponds roughly to “use
am/pm time in the Americas and 24 hour time everywhere else.” In practice,
that’s a locale setting with more nuance, but this simplification probably
satisfies most of the likely audience.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the schedule includes 12:00 in local time, it is displayed as either
“midday” or “noon” depending on the time display: midday if the 24 hour display
is used, noon otherwise.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the schedule includes 00:00 in local time, it is displayed as “midnight”.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If midnight occurs within the schedule, “<code>&lt;br> (the next day)</code>”
must be added to the displayed times that occur after midnight.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>If the table is successfully constructed, the content of the <code>p</code>
element on the page that has the id “<code>schedlink</code>” must be changed to:
</para>
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<a href='#schedule'>Interactive schedule-at-a-glance</a>]]></programlisting>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section xml:id="markup">
<title>Markup</title>

<para>Historically, the schedule page was the “single source of truth”
used to generate both web pages and a printed conference program. Consequently,
the existing editorial process already adds sufficient markup to correctly
identify the salient details about each talk: when it occurs, the title,
authors, and so forth. You can easily explore this markup with “view source”
on the schedule page.</para>

<para>In brief: there’s a <code>div</code> for each day. Each event has
its own <code>div</code> within the day. The date and time, title, speakers,
and abstract are encoded within that div. By way of example,
<xref linkend="figmarkup"/> shows how a talk scheduled for Monday at
10:00am would be tagged.</para>

<figure xml:id="figmarkup">
<title>Scheduled event markup example</title>
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<div class="Program-Day" id="Monday">
  <h1>Monday, August 2, 2021</h1>
  <div class="ProgramEvent" id="M10">
    <span class="EventDateTime">
      <span class="Day">Monday</span>
      <span class="timestart">10:00</span>
      <span class="timeend">10:30 EDT</span></span>
      (+ Q&amp;A 10:30 - 10:50)
      <h2 class="EventTitle">The Title of the Talk</h2>
      <h2 class="Speakers">
          <a class="biolink" href="Bios.html#xxx">
            <span class="SpeakerName">J. Doe</span></a>,
            <span class="affil">Some affiliation</span>
      </h2>
      <p class="blurb">A short abstract of the talk.</p>
  </div>
  …]]></programlisting>
</figure>

</section>

<section xml:id="browsers">
<title>Observations about browser architecture</title>

<para>All three of the solutions discussed here ultimately run in the
browser, using the architecture and features exposed there. XForms
takes a robustly declarative position, freeing the user from many of
the details, but the XForms <emphasis>implementation</emphasis> is
still operating within the browser architecture.</para>

<para>The programming language environment supported by the browser is
JavaScript. (There are XSLT 1.0 implementations as well in some
browsers, but XSLT 1.0 stylesheets by themselves, as supported by
browsers, aren’t sufficient to write interactive applications.)
JavaScript is an interesting language. A full exploration of the
features of JavaScript is well beyond our scope here. For our
purposes, <emphasis>in this paper</emphasis>, it’s sufficient to think
of JavaScript as a procedural programming language with a syntax in
the style of C and Java. It is much more than “just” a procedural
programming language, but we don’t need its advanced features
(objects, prototypes, promises, etc.) for this simple application.
</para>

<para>Browser implementations of JavaScript provide complete and
robust access to the HTML documents rendered by the browser. They do
not, natively, provide especially robust access to XML documents or
XML document APIs. Most JavaScript applications use JSON to store
data, not XML. The easiest data structures to create, query, and
update in the browser using JavaScript are JSON objects and arrays.</para>

<para>There are rich JavaScript APIs for accessing information about
the state of the browser, the web page being displayed, and the state
of individual controls on the web page. You can easily, for example,
ask if a checkbox is or is not checked. You can easily change its
state as well. There are also APIs for querying and updating the
values of class attributes, CSS properties, etc.</para>

<para>JavaScript is single threaded: if your
browser is doing one thing in JavaScript, it can’t simultaneously be
doing something else. In addition, the scheduler, the part of the
browser that decides what bit of JavaScript to run, isn’t preemptive.
If you write JavaScript code that “busy waits” for something to
finish, you’re not just blocking your thread, you’re blocking
<emphasis>all</emphasis> the threads. If you’ve ever seen the browser
dialog box that says “this page isn’t responding, do you want to kill
it or continue waiting?”, you’ve seen what happens if a thread busy
waits for too long.</para>

<para>In order to avoid this, JavaScript programmers have to use
“callback functions”. Imagine that your JavaScript code is going to
run a query to find something on the page, a particular
<code>div</code>, for example, and then process it. A naive
implementation would ask the browser to run the query, wait for it to
return the result, and then process it.</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[// This looks a little bit like JavaScript,
// but it's just pseudo-code

let myDiv = document.find("div.ProgramEvent");
processMyDiv(myDiv);]]></programlisting>

<para>There are lots of other
JavaScript functions waiting in the wings to run (even if you didn’t
write them, chunks of the browser itself are waiting for their turn to
run). Waiting for something to finish is bad practice.
It’s your responsibility to give up control and let someone else
have a turn!</para>

<para>What you do instead of waiting, and what many JavaScript APIs force you to do,
is tell the engine what function to “call back” when the query results are ready.</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[// More pseudo-code
document.find("div.ProgramEvent", processMyDiv);]]></programlisting>

<para>Execution of your script stops at the point where you call
<code>document.find</code>. Someone else gets their turn, and when the
results are ready, your <code>processMyDiv</code> function will be called.
This mostly works just fine, even if it’s a little confusing at first.</para>

<para>Thing is, this is <emphasis>so</emphasis> common, that it would
be tedious if you had to write a separate, named function (like
<code>processMyDiv</code>) for every callback you used. JavaScript
lets you just inline the function. Again, this may look a little
confusing, but you get used to it.</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[// One final bit of pseudo-code
document.find("div.ProgramEvent", function() {
  // just write the code that processes the
  // div right here.
});]]></programlisting>

<para>Another area where callback functions come into play is in
handling events. From the perspective of your application, the browser
is “out there” displaying HTML elements, scrolling the page, reacting
to mouse clicks, and doing all the things that the browser does. These
are all represented in the browser as events that occur: a button was
clicked, the page scrolled, a web request finished, etc. There are
lots and lots of kinds of events, we won’t try to enumerate them all
here.
</para>

<para>If your application wants to participate, it needs to tell the browser
what events it cares about. It does that by registering a special kind of callback
function, an event listener:</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[a_button.addEventListener('change', function(event) {
  // do something in response to the event
});]]></programlisting>

<para>When the “this item changed” event occurs on the page element
identified by “<code>a_button</code>”, the “listening” callback
function will be run.
</para>

<para>There’s lots more that could be said about JavaScript, including new features
that are syntactically nicer than all those callback functions, but that’s enough
of the conceptual framework for now.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="pojs">
<title>Plain old JavaScript</title>
<para role="glance">At a glance: satisfies all the requirements, +6K download.</para>
<!-- 6K for the JS alone, not counting Program.html -->

<para>Two browser APIs form the heart of the plain old JavaScript
solution: query selectors and “inner HTML”. Query selectors come in
two forms: <code>querySelector</code> and <code>querySelectorAll</code>.
Each takes a CSS selector as an expression and returns matching
nodes. When called from the <code>document</code> object, the selector
applies to the whole document. When called from some other node, such as one
returned by an earlier query, the selector applies to the
descendants of that node. Where <code>querySelector</code> returns
the first match, <code>querySelectorAll</code> returns all the matches.</para>

<para>For example,</para>

<programlisting language="javascript">document.querySelectorAll("div.ProgramEvent")</programlisting>

<para>returns all of the <code>div</code> elements with the <code>ProgramEvent</code> class.
If you look back at the markup example in <xref linkend="figmarkup"/>, you’ll see that
that is the wrapper for each scheduled talk. You can process those elements
with a JavaScript <code>forEach</code> and our friend, the callback function:</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[
document.querySelectorAll("div.ProgramEvent")
        .forEach(function(item) {
                   // ProgramEvent processing goes here
                 })]]></programlisting>

<para>You can nest these API calls and callbacks arbitrarily.
To finish our little detour into the mechanics of the query
selector APIs, here’s an example that will process each event and write the
day of the week to the console:</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[
document.querySelectorAll("div.ProgramEvent")
        .forEach(function(item) {
                   console.log(item.querySelector("span.Day"))
                 })]]></programlisting>

<para>The only difference is that
<code>querySelector("span.Day")</code> is rooted at the
<code>item</code> we’re currently processing to get the first
<code>span</code> element with the <code>Day</code> class. That’s the
day of the week for this event.
</para>

<para>If you run that code in the browser console, you’ll get all of the day spans:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<span class="Day">Monday</span>
<span class="Day">Monday</span>
…
<span class="Day">Monday</span>
<span class="Day">Tuesday</span>
…]]></programlisting>

<para>The other API that plays a central role is “<code>innerHTML</code>”. The
inner HTML of an element is its HTML content, as a string. You can read from
<code>innerHTML</code> to get the content, but you can also <emphasis>write</emphasis>
to it to change the content.</para>

<para>In other words,</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[document.querySelector("table caption").innerHTML]]></programlisting>

<para>returns “Interactive schedule-at-a-glance” (if you’re on the
schedule page). But</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[document.querySelector("table caption").innerHTML =
   "<span>Hello <i>everyone</i>!</span>"]]></programlisting>

<para>Will change the caption to “Hello <emphasis>everyone</emphasis>!”.
If you’ve got your browser handy,
try it and see!</para>

<para>Armed with these JavaScript APIs, the task isn’t too difficult.</para>

<para>JavaScript is neither especially declarative nor necessarily functional.
The cheap-and-cheerful approach here is to make a few passes over the document
with <code>querySelectorAll</code>, <code>querySelector</code> and <code>innerHTML</code>
to build a summary data structure.
</para>
<para>For each talk, we construct a little JSON object containing the relevant details.
For example:
</para>
<programlisting language="javascript">const talk = {
  "day": "Monday",
  "dtstart": "12:00",
  "dtend": "12:30 EDT",
  "title": "XSLT 3.0 on ordinary prose",
  "blurb": "You work with text and documents for a living,…",
  "authors": ["Norman Tovey-Walsh"]
};</programlisting>

<para>And we insert those into a global object, <code>talks</code> with the
value that will be in the <code>data-slot</code> attribute as the key:</para>
<programlisting language="javascript">const key = talk["day"] + "/" + talk["dtstart"];
talks[key] = talk;</programlisting>

<para>Next, we use <code>querySelector</code> to find the table and nested
<code>querySelectorAll</code> calls to process each row and cell.
</para>

<para>If the cell has a <code>data-slot</code> attribute, we populate it by
writing to <code>innerHTML</code>, otherwise we just copy its contents.
There’s a little bit of fiddling with the class attribute, but the browser
has simple APIs for that sort of thing.</para>

<para>We have to do two more things: we have to adjust the times to the local
time zone and we have to arrange for the browser to run the adjustment whenever
the user changes the timezone, or the 24 hour clock checkbox.</para>

<para>The actual adjustment is straightforward. If we know what the offset is between
the time in Rockville and the time zone to display, we simply add that offset (possibly
negative) to the time, do a few small cosmetic adjustments (12 or 24 hour clock, etc.)
and display the result:</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[function adjustTime(item) {
  let timez = item.getAttribute("datetime");
  // We assume timez is in ISO 8601 format
  let hours = timez.substring(11,13);
  let minutes = timez.substring(14, 16);

  hours = parseInt(hours) + OFSHOURS;
  minutes = parseInt(minutes) + OFSMINUTES;

  while (minutes >= 60) {
    hours += 1;
    minutes -= 60;
  }

  let plusday = "";
  if (hours >= 24) {
    plusday = "<br />(the next day)";
    hours -= 24;
  }

  let ampm = 'am';
  if (!CLOCK24 && hours >= 12) {
    if (hours > 12) {
      hours -= 12;
    }
    ampm = 'pm';
  }

  if (CLOCK24) {
    hours = hours.toString().padStart(2, "0");
  } else {
    hours = hours.toString().padStart(2, " ");
  }

  minutes = minutes.toString().padStart(2, "0");

  let timel = hours + ":" + minutes;
  if (!CLOCK24) {
    timel = timel + ampm;
  }

  if (hours == 0 && minutes == 0) {
    timel = "midnight";
    plusday = "";
  }

  if (hours == 12 && minutes == 0) {
    if (CLOCK24) {
      timel = "midday";
    } else {
      timel = "noon";
    }
    plusday = "";
  }

  item.innerHTML = timel + plusday;
}]]></programlisting>

<para>The key ingredients in that function are the <code>OFSHOURS</code>,
<code>OFSMINUTES</code>, and <code>CLOCK24</code>. Those values come from the user’s
selections. We listen for when the timezone is changed:</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[let timezone = document.querySelector("#tz");
timezone.addEventListener('change', function() {
  adjustOffset(this);
}, false);]]></programlisting>

<para>The <code>adjustOffset</code> function is passed the select
control. The selected option is identified by the <code>selecedIndex</code>
property on that control. That gives us access to the selected timezone.
</para>

<para>From there, we compute the offsets and the default value of the
24 hour clock, then we run <code>adjustTime</code> on each time value:</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[function adjustOffset(item) {
  let tz = item.options[item.selectedIndex].value;
  let pos = tz.indexOf(":");
  let hours = tz.substring(0, pos);
  let minutes = tz.substring(pos+1);
  OFSHOURS = parseInt(hours) + ROCKVILLE_OFFSET;
  OFSMINUTES = parseInt(minutes);

  if (OFSHOURS > 0) {
    document.querySelector("#clock24").checked = true;
    CLOCK24 = true;
  } else {
    document.querySelector("#clock24").checked = false;
    CLOCK24 = false;
  }

  document.querySelectorAll("time").forEach(adjustTime);
}]]></programlisting>

<para>A similar listener function adjusts the <code>CLOCK24</code> value
when the checkbox changes and recomputes the times.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="saxon-js">
<title>Saxon-JS</title>
<para role="glance">At a glance: satisfies all the requirements, 6K stylesheet (42K compiled),
plus Saxon-JS (3M) download.</para>

<para>If you are familiar with XSLT, you will probably recognize a
common design pattern in this task. What we want to perform is an
“almost identity transformation” on the table, adjusting the content
of just those cells that have a <code>data-slot</code> attribute.
Having an XSLT processor in the browser lets us leverage those common
design patterns directly.</para>

<para>It’s easy to match the cells that have a <code>data-slot</code>
attribute. Finding the corresponding <code>ProgramEvent</code> object can
be accomplished directly with a key:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:key name="slot" match="div[@class='ProgramEvent']"
         use="span[@class='EventDateTime']/span[@class='Day']
              || '/'
              || span[@class='EventDateTime']/span[@class='timestart']"/>]]></programlisting>

<para>So the heart of our table transformation is just this simple template:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:template match="td[@data-slot]">
  <xsl:variable name="event" select="key('slot', @data-slot)"/>

  <xsl:choose>
    <xsl:when test="$event">
      <!-- copy the event details into the table -->
    </xsl:when>
    <xsl:otherwise>
      <!-- mark this cell as "No talk scheduled" -->
    </xsl:otherwise>
  </xsl:choose>
</xsl:template>]]></programlisting>

<para>Like JavaScript, Saxon-JS has APIs for interacting with the
browser. Idiomatically, they’re exposed as XSLT extension functions
and extension elements, but they’re very similar to JavaScript. This
shouldn’t be a surprise as Saxon-JS <emphasis>is</emphasis> JavaScript
running in the browser using the underlying JavaScript APIs on your
stylesheet’s behalf.</para>

<para>Let’s step back and look at how those APIs work.</para>

<para>At the top of our web page, we need to load Saxon-JS and a small JavaScript hook
to start the ball rolling. (In practice, the hook function can be inserted directly in the
HTML page with a <code>script</code> element, but Norm has chosen to keep it outside to
satisfy his aesthetic sensibilities.)</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" src="js/SaxonJS2.rt.js"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="js/start.js"></script>]]></programlisting>

<para>The startup script is just a function assigned to the browsers
“onload” event so that it runs automatically when the page is
loaded:</para>

<programlisting language="javascript"><![CDATA[function render_schedule() {
  let options = { stylesheetLocation: "xslt/schedule.sef.json" };
  SaxonJS.transform(options, "async");
}

window.onload = render_schedule;]]></programlisting>

<!--* MSM adds final line after looking in vain for the assignment
    * to onload.
    *-->

<para>Saxon-JS evaluates a compiled form of XSLT stored in a “SEF”
file, most often in a JSON document. XSLT stylesheets can be compiled
with Saxon-EE or with Saxon-JS running on Node. That step just becomes
part of your build process, analogous to minifying CSS or JavaScript
for web delivery.</para>

<!--* MSM admits to not really knowing what Node is. *-->

<para>The Saxon-JS APIs that form the heart of the solution are
<code>ixsl:page()</code> and <code>xsl:result-document</code>.</para>

<para>Execution of the stylesheet will begin in the initial template.
The HTML page isn’t the global context item because the HTML data
model and the XPath Data Model are not exactly the same. Instead, the
<code>ixsl:page()</code> function is used to access the HTML page.
This function returns an object which “shims up” the HTML page for XDM
access.</para>

<para>With the <code>ixsl:page()</code> document in hand, you have the full power
of XPath and XSLT to query and transform it. But where does the output go?
Enter <code>xsl:result-document</code>. The content of <code>xsl:result-document</code>
is output to the location identified by the <code>href</code> attribute.
In Saxon-JS, this concept has been extended such that if the
<code>href</code> attribute begins with a “#” sign, the output goes into
the browser page in the element with the corresponding ID. This instruction:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:result-document href="#main">
  <div>New content</div>
</xsl:result-document>]]></programlisting>

<para>adds the “new content” <code>div</code> to the end of the
element with the id “<code>main</code>” in the document. There’s an
extension attribute as well, <code>method</code>. This instruction:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:result-document href="#caption" method="ixsl:replace-content">
  <span>Hello <i>everyone</i>!</span>
</xsl:result-document>]]></programlisting>

<para>Will change the content of the element with the id “<code>caption</code>”
to “Hello <emphasis>everyone</emphasis>!”.</para>

<para>(Keen observers may have noticed that the table <code>caption</code> on the schedule
at a glance page doesn’t <emphasis>have</emphasis> an ID. That’s ok. We can use
<code>xsl:result-document</code> to update any element on the page. If it doesn’t
have an ID, we can arrange for that element to be the context node and use
<code>href="?."</code> to change it.)</para>

<para>Saxon-JS manages event listeners with special modes. These templates fire when
a user changes the timezone or clicks on the 24 hour clock checkbox:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:template mode="ixsl:onchange" match="select[@id='tz']">
  <xsl:apply-templates select="ixsl:page()" mode="update-times">
    <xsl:with-param name="changetz" select="true()"/>
  </xsl:apply-templates>
</xsl:template>

<xsl:template mode="ixsl:onclick" match="input[@id='clock24']">
  <xsl:apply-templates select="ixsl:page()" mode="update-times"/>
</xsl:template>]]></programlisting>

<para>That code is mostly straight-forward XSLT:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xsl:template match="/" mode="update-times">
  <xsl:param name="changetz" select="false()"/>

  <xsl:variable name="zone"
                select="ixsl:get(//select[@id='tz'], 'value')"/>

  <xsl:variable name="hours"
                select="xs:integer(substring-before($zone, ':'))"/>
  <xsl:variable name="minutes"
                select="xs:integer(substring-after($zone, ':'))"/>

  <xsl:variable name="iso8601"
                select="(if ($hours lt 0) then '-' else '')
                        || 'PT' || abs($hours)
                        || 'H' || $minutes || 'M'"/>

  <xsl:if test="$changetz">
    <ixsl:set-property name="checked"
                       select="$hours ge 0"
                       object="//input[@id='clock24']"/>
  </xsl:if>

  <xsl:variable name="ampm"
                select="not(ixsl:get(//input[@id='clock24'], 'checked'))"/>

  <xsl:variable name="format"
                select="if ($ampm)
                        then '[h1]:[m01][P]'
                        else '[H01]:[m01]'"/>

  <xsl:variable name="tz" select="xs:dayTimeDuration($iso8601)"/>
  <xsl:for-each select="//div[@id='schedule']//time">
    <xsl:variable name="conftime"
                  select="xs:dateTime(@datetime)"/>
    <xsl:variable name="dt"
                  select="adjust-dateTime-to-timezone($conftime, $tz)"/>
    <xsl:result-document href="?." method="ixsl:replace-content">
      <xsl:choose>
        <xsl:when test="hours-from-dateTime($dt) = 0
                        and minutes-from-dateTime($dt) = 0">
          <xsl:text>midnight</xsl:text>
        </xsl:when>
        <xsl:when test="hours-from-dateTime($dt) = 12
                        and minutes-from-dateTime($dt) = 0">
          <xsl:sequence select="if ($ampm) then 'noon' else 'midday'"/>
        </xsl:when>
        <xsl:otherwise>
          <xsl:sequence select="format-dateTime($dt, $format)"/>
          <xsl:if test="day-from-dateTime($conftime) != day-from-dateTime($dt)">
            <br/>
            <xsl:text> (the next day)</xsl:text>
          </xsl:if>
        </xsl:otherwise>
      </xsl:choose>
    </xsl:result-document>
  </xsl:for-each>
</xsl:template>]]></programlisting>

<para>It’s certainly nice to have access to the XPath datetime
functions! Also noteworthy are a couple of calls to
<code>ixsl:get</code>, another extension function. This one gives you
access to JavaScript properties. And <code>?.</code> as the
<code>href</code> value for <code>xsl:result-document</code> when you
want to write to the current context node, whether it has an id or
not.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="xforms">
<title>XForms</title>

<para role="glance">At a glance: XForms resists some aspects of the task as
specified, but satisfies all the requirements, mostly in pure standard
XForms with some implementation-specified extensions, 800K download
for the XSLTForms implementation of XForms (partly XSLT, partly
Javascript).<!-- not counting Program.xhtml itself -->
</para>

<para>XForms is designed as a declarative language for making forms in
web pages.  It is XML-based: it uses XPath to identify elements and
specify values, and when it submits data to a server, it does so in
XML. If there is not too much mixed content, XForms can be thought of
as a general tool for making special-purpose XML editors.
Interactivity in existing documents is not its main goal, but its
declarative mechanisms for user interaction make it a useful tool for
such tasks.  From an XForms point of view, the core tasks imposed by
the constraints outlined above are, first, to maintain information
about the schedule and modify it in response to user actions, and,
second, to display the current form of that information to the
user.</para>

<para>Since the usual XForms mechanisms for displaying information to
the user do not involve modifying the form&#x2019;s host document, the parts
of the problem description that prescribe that mechanism for conveying
information to the user don&#x2019;t fit comfortably in the usual XForms
patterns.  The result is that the goal of simplifying comparison by
making all three solutions as similar as possible is in tension with
writing the form in normal idiomatic XForms.</para>

<para>In an XForm, the information displayed to the user comes in part
from the form document itself and in part from XML <emphasis
role="ital">instance documents</emphasis> which are managed and
manipulated by the form.  The form is written in a <emphasis
role="ital">host</emphasis> document language chosen by the XForms
processor, extended with XForms elements.  For this exercise the host language is
XHTML, but XForms can be and has been implemented for other host XML
vocabularies instead.  The XForms extensions to the host vocabulary
fall into two classes: elements for specifying the XML document
instances to be worked on and constraints that govern the documents
and their manipulation (<code>xf:model</code>,
<code>xf:instance</code>, <code>xf:bind</code>, and others) on the one
hand, and on the other hand elements for specifying, within the displayable
part of a form, that particular parts of the XML instances documents
should be displayed or made accessible for interaction
(<code>xf:input</code>, <code>xf:output</code> and other controls, as
well as markup for specifying event-handling rules).  As may be
inferred, XForms makes a strict distinction between the XML documents
being manipulated and the user interface through which that
manipulation occurs, in a way reminiscent of the Model / View /
Controller idiom.
</para>

<para>In XHTML-based XForms, the document instances and constraints
are usually specified within the HTML header, wrapped in an
<code>xf:model</code> element.  The interaction controls, by contrast,
are placed at appropriate locations in the HTML body.  We&#x2019;ll start by
showing the XForm implementation of the timezone selector and the
24-hour-clock checkbox, which are straightforward applications of core
XForms ideas, and then other aspects of the problem: how to inject
HTML into the host document of a form, how the timezone calculations
can be implemented in XForms, and a simple application of XForms
facilities for event handling.</para>

<para>Before we do, some notes on the implementation may be in order
and may as well be taken care of now.</para>

<para>First, there are multiple XForms implementations, which vary in
approach.  Some have gaps in their coverage of the specification, and
many offer extensions to the spec.  This implementation uses
XSLTForms, a well known open source XForms engine which uses the
browser&#x2019;s XSLT 1.0 engine to transform the user-written XHTML + XForms
source document into pure HTML in the browser, and a Javascript
library to support XForms functionality within the browser.  XSLTForms
offers very simple setup &#x2014; the only thing the form author has
to do is install the stylesheet and Javascript library on their server
and point to the stylesheet from the form.  Other implementations use
a different approach, often providing a server-side component which
handles some tasks.  The implementation described here mostly uses
standard XForms 1.1 and would look the same whatever XForms engine was
used; when extensions specific to XSLTforms are used, the fact will be
noted.</para>

<para>Second, there are multiple versions of XForms.  The form
described here uses XForms 1.1, which became a W3C Recommendation in
2009.  Some implementations have also implemented parts of XForms 2.0,
which is currently under development in a W3C community group, but the
authors&#x2019; knowledge of XForms has not yet caught up to XForms
2.0; where we are aware that an XForms 2.0 solution to this problem might take a
different form, that fact may be noted.</para>

<para>Third, there are multiple ways to satisfy the given
requirements in XForms.  The implementation currently on hand is not
necessarily the best.  Some of the more obvious alternative methods
will be mentioned below, but they have not yet been implemented.
Between now and August, some of them may be.  The current plan is to
leave the current implementation in place, and put one or more
alternative implementations beside it on the public server.  The paper
will be updated accordingly.</para>

<section xml:id="xf-controls">

<title>Simple user-interaction controls and the ui instance</title>

<para>In this exercise, the direct user interaction is very simple and
rather limited: the user gets a way to select a time zone, and a way
to specify whether a 24-hour clock or a 12-hour clock is to be
used. For selecting one value from a controlled list of values, XForms
uses the <code>xf:select1</code> control.  In rough outline, the
time zone control looks like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<xf:select1 id="timezone-selector" ref="instance('ui')/tz">
  <xf:label>Timezone: </xf:label>
  ...
  <xf:item>
    <xf:label>CDT  Chicago, IL, USA (UTC-05:00)</xf:label>
    <xf:value>-05:00</xf:value>
  </xf:item>
  <xf:item>
    <xf:label>EDT  Rockville, MD, USA (UTC-04:00)</xf:label>
    <xf:value>-04:00</xf:value>
  </xf:item>
  ...
  <xf:item>
    <xf:label>CEST Prague, CZE (UTC+02:00)</xf:label>
    <xf:value>+02:00</xf:value>
  </xf:item>
  ...
</xf:select1>
]]></programlisting>

<para>The basic structure will be familiar to many who have written
forms: the control contains a list of possible values, each with the
label to be used in offering the choice to the user.  The list of
options is wrapped in a <code>xf:select1</code> element, which
describes not the user interface widget to be presented to the user,
but the semantic affect to be achieved: the user should select one
value from among those listed.  Whether the display engine uses a
pull-down menu, a fully expanded menu, radio buttons, or some other
mechanism to achieve that effect is not specified in the form or in
the XForms spec.  (An <code>appearance</code> attribute with possible
values <code>full</code>, <code>compact</code>, and
<code>minimal</code> can be used to give hints about what would work
best. At that level of abstraction, a form processor working in a
voice browser can try to make appropriate adjustments.)  Note that the
<code>xf:label</code> element appears at both levels: one label for
the selection control as a whole and one for each item.  By
associating the label structurally with the thing labeled, XForms
makes it easier for software to understand the logical structure of
the form, which is why it provides a better experience for users
employing voice browsers and assistive technologies.</para>

<para>But where is the selected time zone actually stored, once the
user selects one?</para>

<para>XForms 1.0 and 1.1 do not define variables; all controls are
bound to nodes in XML document instances.  A common idiom, when the
form needs to keep track of information that is not in any of the XML
documents the form works with, is to add a document instance to
contain that information and allow the form to manage it.  In this
case, the information is all concerned with the state of the user
interface, so the instance has been given the name <emphasis
role="ital">ui</emphasis>.  Like the other instances used, the
<emphasis role="ital">ui</emphasis> instance appears in the HTML
header, inside the <code>xf:model</code> element, which in outline
looks like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<head>
  <title>Balisage 2020 Program</title>
  ...

  <xf:model id="m1">

    <xf:instance id="program" src="./Program.xhtml"/>

    <xf:instance id="ui" xmlns="">
      <ui-info clock24="false">
        <tz>-04:00</tz>
	...
      </ui-info>
    </xf:instance>
    ...
  </xf:model>
  ...
</head>]]></programlisting>

<para>As can be seen, the <code>ui</code> instance
has a <code>clock24</code> attribute on the root
element and a child element named <code>tz</code>,
and a bit more not shown here.</para>

<para>The <code>ref</code> attribute on the <code>xf:select1</code>
control binds the control to the <code>tz</code>
element using the XPath expression <code>instance('ui')/tz</code>.
The XForms function <code>instance()</code> identifies the
outermost element of an instance document; <code>instance('ui')</code>
thus refers to the <code>ui-info</code> element shown in the
model.<footnote>
<para>Users of XPath in other contexts may find themselves expecting
<code>instance()</code> to bind to the instance&#x2019;s document node
instead of to that node&#x2019;s single element child; a common error for
such users would be to write <code>instance('ui')/ui-info/tz</code>
instead of the correct XPath, in this example.</para>
</footnote>
The result of the binding is that when the control is used to select a
timezone, the value in the instance document is updated
automatically.</para>

<para>The 24-hour clock checkbox is simpler.  It uses the
<code>xf:input</code> element:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:input ref="instance('ui')/@clock24">
  <xf:label>24-hour clock: </xf:label>
</xf:input>]]></programlisting>

<para>If the form knew nothing about the <code>clock24</code>
attribute, this would be roughly equivalent to an HTML
<code>input</code> element of type <code>text</code>.  But if we tell
the form that the attribute holds a Boolean value, the form can use a
more appropriate interface like a checkbox to present the value to the
user.  This we do with an <code>xf:bind</code> element which
identifies a node in an instance document and identifies its (XSD)
datatype.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/@clock24"
         type="xsd:boolean" />]]></programlisting>

<para>The <code>xf:bind</code> element has other uses, some of which
will be seen later.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="xf-injection">
<title>Injecting HTML into the host document</title>

<para>Because XForms is designed to display and allow user interaction
with nodes in the document instances of the model, and not to modify
the nodes of the host document itself, the parts of the exercise which
specify that various pieces of information be injected into specific
places in the conference program require a little adjustment in
XForms.</para>

<para>The simplest example is perhaps the final item in the <link
linkend="requirements">requirements list</link>.  In the Javascript
and Saxon-JS solutions, an HTML <code>p</code> element in the program
is given HTML content.  The element originally looks like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<p id="schedlink"></p>]]></programlisting>

<para>In the browser, it is to be modified to take the following form,
or an equivalent:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<p id="schedlink">
  &#x261E; Interactive
  <a href="#schedule">schedule at a glance</a>.
</p>]]></programlisting>

<para>This particular implementation tactic is not open to XForms, but
we can do something conceptually similar.  In the XForms solution to
the task, the conference program is modified so that the paragraph in
question contains an <code>xf:output</code> element, which XForms uses
to display data from an instance document.<footnote>
<para>This may have the advantage of making more obvious to casual
observers that the <code>schedlink</code> paragraph is not a mistake
or tag abuse (as empty paragraphs often are in HTML) but a container
for information to be supplied at display time.  New collaborators may
be less likely to delete the element as part of &#x2018;cleaning up the
accumulated cruft&#x2019; in the program document.</para>
</footnote></para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<p id="schedlink">
  <xf:output mediatype="text/html"
             ref="instance('ui')/schedlink"/>
</p>]]></programlisting>

<para>The <code>mediatype</code> attribute on <code>xf:output</code>
indicates the data format of the data to be displayed. (Operationally,
it says &#x201C;take this string and write it to the
<code>innerHTML</code> property of the containing element.&#x201D;)
The <code>mediatype</code> attribute is
particularly helpful for allowing the display of image data, but as
can be seen here it can also be used to inject HTML elements into the
display of the form.  The <code>ref</code> attribute links this output
control to the <code>schedlink</code> element in the <code>ui</code>
instance document.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:model id="m1">
    ...
    <xf:instance id="ui" xmlns="">
      <ui-info clock24="false">
        <tz>-04:00</tz>
        ...
        <schedlink>
          &#x261E; Interactive
          <a href="#schedule">schedule at a glance</a>.
        </schedlink>
      </ui>
    </xf:instance>

    <xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/@clock24"
             type="xsd:boolean" />

    ...
    </xf:model>]]></programlisting>

<para>The same pattern is used in the main part of the tabular
display.  Since an XForm cannot change elements in its host document,
we need to introduce <code>xf:output</code> elements to show where the
titles and authors of talks need to be displayed.  So the
<code>td</code> elements of the framework table are no longer empty.
In the current workflow, for example, the first slot on Monday takes
the following form.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<td rowspan="2" data-slot="Monday/10:00"></td>]]></programlisting>

<para>In the XForm, it contains XForms elements to specify what needs
to be displayed there:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<td rowspan="2" data-slot="Monday/10:00">
  <xf:group
      ref="instance('program')//xhtml:div
           [@class='ProgramEvent']
	   [xhtml:span[@class='EventDateTime']
           [xhtml:span[@class='Day'
	               and string() = 'Monday']]
           [xhtml:span[@class='timestart'
		       and string() = '10:00']]
           ]">
    <xf:output value="xhtml:h2[@class='EventTitle']"/>
    <span> &#x2014; </span>
    <xf:repeat
        nodeset="xhtml:h2[@class='Speakers']/xhtml:a">
      <xf:output mediatype="text/html"
                 value="serialize(.)"/>
    </xf:repeat>
  </xf:group>
</td>]]></programlisting>

<para>As may be seen, this complicates the input significantly.  A
simpler approach is to use the <code>transform()</code> function, an
extension offered by XSLTforms, which allows an XSLT stylesheet to be
invoked on a specified node in an instance document.  Using that
approach, the same slot looks like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<td rowspan="2" data-slot="Monday/10:00">
  <xf:output mediatype="text/html"
             value="transform(instance('program'),
                              'single-item.xsl',
			      false,
			      'slot',
			      'Monday/10:00')"/>
</td>]]></programlisting>

<para>The <code>xf:output</code> element here essentially says that
the value to be displayed (as HTML) is whatever is produced by
invoking the XSLT 1.0 stylesheet <code>single-item.xsl</code> on the
<code>program</code> instance, with the stylesheet parameter
<code>slot</code> given the string value
<code>Monday/10:00</code>.<footnote>
<para>Some readers will wonder what the third argument of the function
call means.  It&#x2019;s a Boolean flag indicating (if true) that the second
argument contains a string representation of the stylesheet, or (if
false) that the second argument is a URI which must be dereferenced to
get the stylesheet.</para>
<para>The stylesheet could be invoked on the specific ProgramEvent
<code>div</code> needed, but as seen above the XPath expressions
needed to identify the appropriate element are rather long; it&#x2019;s
simpler to pass the entire program to the stylesheet and find the
appropriate <code>div</code> there.</para>
</footnote></para>

<para>The <code>program</code> instance is, as the name suggests, a
document containing authoritative information about the conference
program.  As explained <link linkend="constraints">above</link>,
that is the HTML document in which the form is embedded.  But an XForm
cannot extract data from its host document any more than it can modify
the host document.  To make the code just given work, therefore, it is
necessary to make the host document available to the XForm <emphasis
role="ital">as an instance document</emphasis>, which is done using an
<code>xf:instance</code> element with the appropriate URI.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:instance id="program" src="./Program.xhtml"/>]]></programlisting>

<para>This is not quite as self-referential as it may look.  In
practice, the browser loads two copies of the file:  one is the XHTML
page actually displayed by the browser,<footnote>
<para>If we are being pedantic, we should note that what the browser
displays is not the document <code>Program.xhtml</code>, which is an
XHTML document with embedded XForms elements, but the result of
processing that document with the <code>xsltforms.xsl</code>
stylesheet, which translates the XForms elements into elements better
understood by Web browsers.  As support for non-HTML elements has
improved, the XSLTForms translation of XForms elements has
changed.</para>
</footnote> and the other is an instance document accessible to the
form.  Changing the HTML in the instance document does not affect the
document being displayed by the browser, except by means of the
<code>xf:output</code> elements shown above.</para>

<para>An alternative implementation approach would resemble the
Javascript and Saxon-JS examples more closely.  In this approach:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>The skeleton of the schedule-at-a-glance table is left as
    is, without the insertion of <code>xf:output</code>
    elements.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>When the program is loaded as an instance document, the form
    updates the program-event cells in the table (in the instance
    document) by locating the talks and injecting the appropriate HTML
    into the table elements.</para>
    <para>This processing is triggered automatically when the form
    processor reports that the instance document has been loaded (by
    dispatching the event <code>xforms-model-construct-done</code>
    to the model).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>When the user selects a new timezone, the resulting time
    displays are injected into the table in the instance document
    and not (as described <link linkend="xf-calculation">below</link>)
    in the <code>ui</code> instance.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The schedule table in the form&#x2019;s host document remains
    unchanged and empty, and it is not displayed.</para>
    <para>Instead, an <code>xf:output</code> element in the program
    displays the schedule table from the instance document.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
This approach is probably preferable, since it involves less change to
the current program document structure.  At the time this submission
was written, however, it had not yet been implemented, mostly because
it was not the first approach found.  (As mentioned already, the idea
of modifying elements in the host document is foreign to normal
practice in XForms.  It took a while for the idea described above to
take shape.)  A second reason is that it requires a firm grasp of
XForms event handling, which is sometimes elusive.
</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="xf-calculation">
<title>Timezone calculations</title>

<para>The core idea of this exercise is to make the document
interactive by making it react appropriately to the user&#x2019;s choice of
timezone.  To do this, we:
<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Replace the literal time indications of the program document
    with <code>xf:output</code> elements pointing to elements in an
    instance document, so they can be changed dynamically.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Add a <code>slot-times</code>
    element to the <code>ui</code> instance document, containing a
    <code>slot</code> element for each time slot in the table.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Calculate new values for the slot elements, whenever the
    user changes the timezone.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<para>In the XForm version of the program document, the table cells
containing the time for each event take the following general
form.  This is the same as the current structure, except for
the addition of the <code>xf:output</code> element.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<th id="r10" class="time" scope="row">
  <time datetime="2020-07-27T10:00:00-04:00">10:00</time>
  <xf:output
      mediatype="text/html"
      value="instance('ui')/slot-times/slot[@id='r10']"/>
</th>]]></programlisting>

<para>As can be seen, the slot elements in the <code>ui</code>
document instance have the same IDs as the corresponding
cells in the table, to simplify joining them up.</para>

<para>In the <code>ui</code> document instance, a slot element has the
following form.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<slot id="r10"
      datetime="2020-07-27T10:00:00-04:00"
      user-datetime="2020-07-27T10:00:00-04:00"
      user-time="" uh24="" uh12="" wrapped=""
      default="10:00">10:00</slot>]]></programlisting>

<para>The <code>id</code> and <code>datetime</code> attributes are
copies of those on the table cell and the <code>time</code> element
inside it.  The <code>default</code> attribute holds the original content
of the table cell, in case we ever need it.  (We don&#x2019;t, as it turns
out, but we didn&#x2019;t know that at first.)  The content of the element is
what will ultimately be displayed to the user.  The other attributes
are there to hold intermediate values, partly as a way of simplifying
the XPath expressions used in the calculation of the element content,
and partly as a way of dividing the time zone calculation up into
manageable pieces. It may be observed that they are initially blank,
because they are only needed when calculating the time for a new time
zone.</para>

<para>The calculation of the event&#x2019;s time in the user&#x2019;s time zone is
handled by a series of <code>xf:bind</code> elements with
<code>calculate</code> attributes.  The <code>calculate</code>
attribute is used, as its name suggests, to calculate the value of
some node from other information already available.  Its value is an
XPath expression.</para>

<para>In an XForms implementation which had full support for XPath 2.0
functions, most of the intermediate values would not be needed and the
entire process could be handled with a simple call to
<code>adjust-dateTime-to-timezone()</code>, followed by a call to
<code>format-dateTime()</code>.  Since the current version of
XSLTforms does not have an XPath 2.0 version of
<code>adjust-dateTime-to-timezone()</code>, we cannot do it this way;
we need to do the timezone arithmetic ourselves.</para>

<para>An alternative approach would be to implement the required XPath
2.0 functions in Javascript and install them as extension functions.
This is possible, but details of how to do it vary among XForms
processors, and it requires using Javascript, which some people try to
avoid when possible.</para>

<para>Since calculating intermediate values by specifying XPath
expressions and storing them in nodes in an XML document is easy to
understand for any XSLT programmer, the <code>xf:bind</code> elements
used to perform the time zone calculations will need hardly any
commentary.  But first we need to explain briefly how the calculations
work.</para>

<para>XForms 1.1 specifies a number of functions for the XPath
function library, including a <code>seconds-from-dateTime()</code>
function which converts a dateTime expression into the number of
seconds separating the dateTime indicated from the epoch at
<code>1970-01-01T00:00:00Z</code>.<footnote><para>It is thus not at
all similar to the XPath 2.0 function defined later under the same
(local) name.</para></footnote> Its opposite number is
<code>seconds-to-dateTime()</code>, which converts an integer number
of seconds into a dateTime in UTC.  We will compute the user&#x2019;s local
time by (1) converting the timezone offset into seconds, (2)
converting the scheduled time of the event into seconds, (3) adding
the two, and (4) converting the resulting number of seconds back into
a dateTime expression.<footnote>
<para>The resulting dateTime expression will use timezone Z (UTC
itself), but it will <emphasis role="ital">not</emphasis> be the UTC
time of the event.  It will be the UTC time at the moment when a
UTC clock shows the same time as the user&#x2019;s local clocks at the
time the event takes place.</para>
<para>The reader can either accept this fact as a kind of black-box
magic, or an example may help make it clear.  Suppose we wish to
calculate the JST equivalent for the 10:00am morning slot.  The event
time of 10:00am is given in a timezone with offset -04:00; the
corresponding UTC time is 14:00 (10:00 + 04:00).  Japanese Standard
Time has an offset from UTC of 09:00.  If we add 9 hours to the UTC
time of 14:00, we get a time of 23:00.  Whether we interpret this
23:00 as (a) the time shown by a clock in UTC timezone Z, 9 hours
after the event time of 14:00 UTC, or (b) the time shown by a clock in
JST at 14:00Z, is immaterial.  The expression returned by the
<code>seconds-to-dateTime()</code> function assumes interpretation
(a), but we can just extract the hours and minutes fields and apply
interpretation (b).  And we do.</para>
</footnote></para>

<para>First, we calculate the timezone offset in seconds by extracting
the number of hours and minutes in the timezone offset value.  To hold
these, we add some blank attributes to the <code>tz</code>
element: <code>&lt;tz h="" m="" sign="-" secs=""></code>.  The values
to be assigned to those attributes are specified in the following bind
elements.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/tz/@h"
         type="xsd:integer"
         calculate="substring(.., 2, 2)"/>
<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/tz/@m"
	 type="xsd:integer"
         calculate="substring(.., 5, 2)"/>
<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/tz/@sign"
         calculate="substring(.., 1, 1)"/>
<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/tz/@secs"
         calculate="if(../@sign = '-',
                    0 - (((../@h * 60) + ../@m) * 60),
                    0 + (((../@h * 60) + ../@m) * 60))"/>]]></programlisting>

<para>It may need to be mentioned that the context item for
interpretation of the <code>calculate</code> attribute is the node
whose value is being calculated.  Thus the calculation of the
<code>h</code> and <code>m</code> attributes must refer to
<code>..</code> to fetch the string value of the <code>tz</code>
element.</para>

<para>The last calculation uses the XForms function
<code>if()</code>, which allows conditionals to be expressed inside
XPath 1.0 expressions.  It takes three arguments: the condition to be
tested, the result if the condition evaluates to true, and the result
if the condition evaluates to false.</para>

<para>Whenever the value of the <code>tz</code> element changes, all
other values which are known to depend on it are recalculated.  The
dependencies expressed in the <code>calculate</code> expressions are
known, and the XForms processor uses the same algorithm as a
spreadsheet processor to decide on the order in which to calculate the
values in any dependency chain.  So no effort is needed on the part of
the form author to specify that <code>h</code> and <code>m</code> and
<code>sign</code> need to be calculated before <code>secs</code>.  The
processor takes care of all that.</para>

<para>The <code>user-datetime</code> value on any slot is calculated
as described above.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/slot-times
                  /slot/@user-datetime"
         type="xsd:dateTime"
         calculate="seconds-to-dateTime(
                    seconds-from-dateTime(../@datetime)
                    +
                    instance('ui')/tz/@secs
                    )"
         />]]></programlisting>

<para>From the <code>user-datetime</code> value, we can extract
several other useful values: the hours-and-minutes part of the
dateTime expression (<code>user-time</code>), the hours part of the
expression on a 24-hour clock (<code>uh24</code>), the hours part on a
12-hour clock (<code>uh12</code>), and finally a Boolean flag to show
whether the clock has moved to the next day or not
(<code>wrapped</code>).</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/slot-times
                  /slot/@user-time"
         type="xsd:string"
         calculate="substring(../@user-datetime, 12, 5)" />
<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/slot-times/slot/@uh24"
         type="xsd:string"
         calculate="substring(../@user-time, 1, 2)" />
<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/slot-times/slot/@uh12"
         type="xsd:string"
         calculate="((../@uh24 + 11) mod 12) + 1" />
<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/slot-times/slot/@wrapped"
         type="xsd:boolean"
         calculate="substring(../@user-datetime, 9, 2)
                    > substring(../@datetime, 9, 2)" />]]></programlisting>

<para>The final calculation of the string to be displayed to the user
is complex enough to be worth explaining in more detail.  The core
calculation is: if the <code>clock24</code> flag is set to
false,<footnote>
<para>The slightly awkward form of the test, checking for both 0 and
&#x201C;false&#x201D;, is an attempt to protect against any flaws in
the form processor&#x2019;s implementation of the <code>xsd:boolean</code>
datatype.  Trying to meet a deadline, it was easier to write this
awkward expression than to establish with complete certainty whether
there is some
simpler formulation of the test that will always work.</para>
</footnote> then concatenate the 12-hour version of the
hour value with a colon and the minutes value, and add either &#x201C;am&#x201D; or
&#x201C;pm&#x201D; as appropriate.  Otherwise (<code>clock24</code> is true), just
use the <code>user-time</code> value, which is on a 24-hour
clock.</para>

<programlisting language="xpath"><![CDATA[
if(instance('ui')/@clock24 = 0
   or instance('ui')/@clock24 = 'false',
   concat(@uh12,
          ':', substring(@user-time, 4, 2),
          if(@uh24 > 11, 'pm', 'am')
         ),

   substring(./@user-datetime, 12, 5)
  )]]></programlisting>

<para>But the time 12:00 should be displayed as &#x201C;noon&#x201D; or as &#x201C;midday&#x201D;,
so the code just given is wrapped in a test for 12:00:</para>

<programlisting language="xpath"><![CDATA[
if(@user-time = '12:00',
   if(instance('ui')/@clock24 = 0
      or instance('ui')/@clock24 = 'false',
      'noon',
      'midday'),
   ... else-case as above ...
  )]]></programlisting>

<para>A second complication is that if the time is past midnight in
the user&#x2019;s timezone, we are to add an HTML <code>br</code> element and
the notice &#x201C;(the next day)&#x201D;.  So the expression just given is wrapped
in a call to <code>concat()</code>, together with a test for the
past-midnight case.</para>

<programlisting language="xpath"><![CDATA[
concat(
       ... time expression as given above ...
       ,
       if(@wrapped = 'true' or @wrapped = 1,
          ' &lt;br />(the next day)',
          '')
      )]]></programlisting>

<para>The final complication is that if the user time is 00:00, then
(a) the time should be displayed as &#x201C;midnight&#x201D;, and (b) the phrase
&#x201C;(the next day)&#x201D; should not be used, since it would raise more
questions than it answers.  The full expression of the final step in
the calculation is thus as follows.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:bind nodeset="instance('ui')/slot-times/slot"
         type="xsd:string"
         calculate="if(@user-time = '00:00',
                    'midnight',

                    concat(
                    if(@user-time = '12:00',
                    if(instance('ui')/@clock24 = 0
		       or instance('ui')/@clock24 = 'false',
                    'noon',
                    'midday'),

                    if(instance('ui')/@clock24 = 0
		       or instance('ui')/@clock24 = 'false',
                    concat(@uh12,
                    ':', substring(@user-time, 4, 2),
                    if(@uh24 > 11, 'pm', 'am')
                    ),

                    substring(./@user-datetime, 12, 5)
                    )),

                    if(@wrapped = 'true' or @wrapped = 1,
                    ' &lt;br />(the next day)',
                    '')
                    ))

                    " />]]></programlisting>

<para>With the help of the <code>xf:bind</code> element, the core
interactivity of the document can be implemented in a purely
declarative way.  As can be seen from the first steps in the sequence,
using instance-document nodes to hold intermediate values can help
make the expressions at each step simpler; as can be seen from the
final calculation, intermediate nodes are not strictly necessary, if
one is willing to work with a more complex expression.</para>

</section>

<section xml:id="xf-events">
<title>Event handling</title>

<para>The final part of the XForms implementation to be explained is
the dependency of the <code>clock24</code> flag on the timezone.
Whenever the timezone changes, the <code>clock24</code> flag should be
updated: for time zones in (roughly) the Western Hemisphere,
<code>clock24</code> should be set false; for timezones in the Eastern
Hemisphere, it should be set true.<footnote><para>This reflects the
mostly true generalization that conference programs in the
U.S. normally use 12-hour times, and conference programs in the rest
of the world are more likely to use 24-hour times.  The reality, of
course, is more complex.  But this gives us the excuse to require
another dynamic change in the document.</para></footnote></para>

<para>We could use <code>xf:bind</code> with a <code>calculate</code>
attribute for this task, but that would effectively prevent the user
from changing the <code>clock24</code> flag: <code>calculate</code>
expresses an invariant relation between values in the instance
document.  We want to change the value, but let the user change it
back.</para>

<para>XForms has an event model similar to (and derived from) that of
the HTML document model as specified in DOM level 2.  At various times
during the life of a form, <emphasis role="ital">events</emphasis> are
dispatched to appropriate targets to be handled by event handlers.
Form authors can register new event handlers which observe specified
locations in the form and can capture and handle them.</para>

<para>For the task at hand, the simplest thing to do is to listen for
the event <code>xforms-value-changed</code> to be dispatched in
response to a change to the <code>tz</code> element, and to handle the
event by setting the value of the <code>clock24</code> attribute
appropriately.  To do this, it suffices to add two
<code>xf:setvalue</code> elements to the <code>xf:select1</code>
element bound to the <code>tz</code> element, thus:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:setvalue ev:event="xforms-value-changed"
             ref="instance('ui')/@clock24"
             value="if(../tz/@sign = '-', 'true', 'false')"/>]]></programlisting>

<para>Here, the <code>ev:event</code> attribute, in the XML Events
namespace, gives the name of the event for which the
<code>xf:setvalue</code> element is listening.  (It does not need to
specify which element it is interested in, because its parent select
controller will only receive events related to the <code>tz</code>
element.)</para>

<para>The <code>ref</code> attribute specifies the node whose value is
to be updated.  The <code>value</code> attribute specifies the new
value.</para>

<para>In principle, this simple approach should solve the problem.
For reasons thus far unexplained (probably an error somewhere in the
form, or possibly in the development version of the engine), however,
this simple approach does not work.  The event is dispatched and
captured, but setting the new value of the <code>clock24</code>
attribute appears to cause an infinite loop.  So until the cause of
the problem is found, another approach is needed.</para>

<para>Since the problem appears to be an infinite loop caused by the
event <code>xforms-value-changed</code> being raised by the handler
for that event, one plausible approach is to try to find some other
event to be used as the trigger for resetting the <code>clock24</code>
flag.</para>

<para>When an item in an <code>xf:select1</code> element is selected,
or de-selected, appropriate events are dispatched to the item.  So we
should be able to reach our goal by putting an event handler on each
item in the timezone selection control and making it listen for the
event <code>xforms-select</code>.  At the same time, partly to
illustrate the user of user-defined events and partly because it makes
it easier to insert debugging messages into the form to report on what
is going on, the <code>xf:setvalue</code> action will be replaced by
an <code>xf:dispatch</code> action which dispatches an appropriate
user-defined event, whose handler will (possibly among other things)
update the <code>clock24</code> flag.</para>

<para>So instead of adding one <code>xf:setvalue</code> element as a
child of <code>xf:select1</code>, we add one <code>xf:dispatch</code>
element to each item in the select control.  The item for Central
Daylight Time (Chicago), for example, looks like this:</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[
<xf:item>
  <xf:label>CDT  Chicago, IL, USA (UTC-05:00)</xf:label>
  <xf:value>-05:00</xf:value>
  <xf:dispatch ev:event="xforms-select"
               targetid="m1"
               name="bmt:set-12h-clock"/>
</xf:item>]]></programlisting>

<para>As before, the <code>ev:event</code> attribute specifies which
events this handler listens for.  The <code>name</code> attribute give
the name of the event to be <emphasis
role="ital">dispatched</emphasis> by the handler, and the
<code>targetid</code> gives the ID of the element which is the target
of the event.  Here, <code>m1</code> is the ID assigned by the form
author to the <code>xf:model</code> element, and
<code>bmt:set-12h-clock</code> is a user-defined event (given as a
QName) meaning the <code>clock24</code> flag should be set
false.<footnote>
<para>The sequence of events will thus be, roughly:  the user
selects CDT as the value of the timezone (element <code>tz</code> in
instance document <code>ui</code>); the forms engine dispatches
event <code>xforms-select</code> to the matching <code>xf:item</code>
in the selection control; the listener (here the
<code>xf:item</code> element) detects the event and invokes any
handlers it has for the event (here, the <code>xf:dispatch</code>
element); the <code>xf:dispatch</code> element dispatches a
<code>bmt:set-12h-clock</code> event to the element with ID
<code>m1</code>, which is the <code>xf:model</code> element in
the header; the model element detects the event and activates
whatever handlers it has for that event, which in this case
is the <code>xf:action</code> event described below.</para>
</footnote>  A
different event (<code>bmt:set-24h-clock</code>) is dispatched by
handlers for time zones east of Greenwich.</para>

<para>Because the event handlers are now embedded in each item in the
selection control, it is easy to make them follow a more complex
pattern than &#x201C;west, 12-hour clock; east, 24-hour clock&#x201D;.
Some sources claim, for example, that most Anglophone countries
normally use 12-hour clocks, and other countries normally use 24-hour
clocks (again, with exceptions and complications not covered here).
If we believe this claim, we can make the selection of Australian or
New Zealand time set the flag to a 12-hour clock, even though they
have a positive timezone offset.</para>

<para>The user-defined events are dispatched to the model, and the
handlers for those events are given as children of the
<code>xf:model</code> element.</para>

<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<xf:model id="m1">
  ...

  <xf:action ev:event="bmt:set-12h-clock">
    <xf:message if="instance('ui')/@debugging = 'true'"
                level="modal"
                >Clock should change to 12h.</xf:message>
    <xf:setvalue ref="instance('ui')/@clock24"
                 value="'false'" />
    <xf:message if="instance('ui')/@debugging = 'true'"
                level="modal"
                >Check it out!  The 24h clock switch <!--
		-->should have changed!</xf:message>
  </xf:action>

  <xf:action ev:event="bmt:set-24h-clock">
    <xf:message if="instance('ui')/@debugging = 'true'"
                level="modal"
                >Clock should change to 24h.</xf:message>
    <xf:setvalue ref="instance('ui')/@clock24"
                 value="'true'" />
    <xf:message if="instance('ui')/@debugging = 'true'"
                level="modal"
                >Did the 24h clock switch?</xf:message>
  </xf:action>
</xf:model>
]]></programlisting>

<para>The <code>xf:action</code> element is a wrapper for other XForms
actions.  It executes them one at a time in turn.  The practical
effect is that the <code>ev:event</code> attribute can be specified
once on the enclosing <code>xf:action</code> and does not need to be
repeated on its children.  The <code>xf:message</code> element
displays a message to the user (here displayed in a popup window, as
suggested by <code>level="modal"</code>).  The
<code>xf:setvalue</code> element has been seen before.</para>

<para>The <code>if</code> attribute seen here on the
<code>xf:message</code> element specifies an arbitrary condition on
the execution of the action.  If the condition holds, the action is
performed, and if not, it is not performed.  Here, a Boolean
<code>debugging</code> attribute on the <code>ui-info</code> element
is tested; if debugging is turned on, the messages are displayed, and
otherwise not.  Messages can in general display useful information
about the course of events; these messages mostly serve to signal that
the event handler has been activated.</para>

</section>

</section>

<section xml:id="conclusion">
<title>Concluding remarks</title>

<para>We are fortunate enought to have multiple ways to provide simple
interactivity for a document that can use it.</para>

<para>The way requirements are specified can influence what solutions
seem most applicable. They’re described in this paper in terms that
make more sense in JavaScript and Saxon-JS than they do in XForms,
though as we’ve demonstrated, they can certainly be accomplished in
XForms.</para>

<para>Javascript is well established both web browsers and elsewhere;
it possesses a very larger user base and its implementations and
libraries correspondingly benefit from intensive development
efforts.  It's not especially declarative, but it can be used easily
for simple tasks like that shown here.</para>

<para>Saxon-JS allows XSLT programmers to leverage their knowledge of
XSLT to provide the required functionality here in a much more
declarative and correspondingly more compact form. The key XSLT 3.0
stylesheet describered here is only 163 lines long (nine templates,
two keys, and an output specification). By providing a comprehensive
XSLT 3.0 implementation in the browser, Saxon-JS brings familiar
design patterns and the XDM’s extensive function library within easy
reach for fully interactive browser applications or server-side
solutions on Node.js.
</para>

<para>XForms also allows a highly declarative description of the
desired interaction; its <code>xf:bind</code> constraints allow
dynamic recalculation of document values, and its support for the
event system implemented in Web browsers makes it possible for an
XForm to react to user actions in dramatic ways.  And if the
<code>transform()</code> extension function is used, XForms also
allows the browser's built-in XSLT 1.0 processor to be invoked
interactively in ways similar to those of Saxon-JS.</para>

<para>The XForm presented here requires more modification of the
existing HTML document than the Javascript or Saxon-JS solutions of
the task.  This is due partly to the more declarative approach taken
by XForms and partly to the fact that the implementor was slow to
hatch the alternative implementation approaches that would have
involved fewer such changes.</para>

<para>We have provided a quick tour of the three sample
implementations of the task; the source code will be available for
inspection, and (assuming we get the continuous-integration pipeline
working) functional versions of all three implementations will be
available for users to experiment with.  Ted Nelson's ideas about
hypertext and interactive documents have not, of course, all been
fully achieved.  But current technologies bring some of them closer to
realization than they have ever been.</para>

</section>
</article>
